<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-06-09T18:14:46+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Paul André, PhD</title><subtitle>This is the personal webpage of Paul André. © Paul André 2023</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Tutorial: making a custom emoji for your Jekyll webpage</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/posts/prgm/custom-emoji/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tutorial: making a custom emoji for your Jekyll webpage" /><published>2023-06-09T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-06-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/posts/prgm/custom_emoji</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/posts/prgm/custom-emoji/"><![CDATA[<p>    <em>Jekyll is probably the most famous static site generator today. It is free, open source and perfect if you need a personal webpage (like the one you are currently reading), or a page dedicated to a project. Many templates exist to help anyone make the best-looking page in a quick and easy way. However, one might want to put an extra personal touch to make the site more memorable and pleasant to navigate. This post proposes a tutorial to integrate custom emojis to your Jekyll webpage.</em></p>

<h2 id="what-are-we-exactly-talking-about">What are we exactly talking about?</h2>

<p>     What I propose here is a rather simple, straightforward, free and open-source way of integrating custom emojis from a drawing (or any picture) to your Jekyll page. This means that, using a simple change of font, you will be able to type and use your own doodles or images as emojis, completely integrated in your posts, with the same layout, font color … as any regular character. This is something that interests me, in pursuit of giving a more playful and personal touch to this page (I like the sobriety of the black and white template, but a little twist never hurts). It will also make it more memorable and recognizable.</p>

<h2 id="step-1-doodling">Step 1: Doodling</h2>

<p>     People who know me are aware that one animal is very dear to my heart, for its weird look and its aura of calm and serenity: the sloth. It is then only logical that I decided to pick this animal as the mascot of this page. I decided to draw the face of a little slothy character and the result is the following one:</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"><img src="/blog/assets/img/emo_1.jpg" alt="Emoji doodle" style="width:300px; height: auto;" class="center" /></p>

<p>Variations of this little face will provide me with emojis suitable for all situations, that I will be able to add in the future at will. It is now time to make this drawing digital, by scanning it and sending it to a computer.</p>

<h2 id="step-2-vectorizing">Step 2: Vectorizing</h2>

<p>     This step requires the help of a software: <a href="https://inkscape.org/">Inkscape</a>. This open-source tool is designed to make vector graphics in an easy way. Vectorizing will make our drawing of choice defined by mathematical statements (instead of pixels) and will be rescalable at will. (Inkscape will be, beyond this tutorial, a great addition to your software library.)</p>

<p>     Going in <span style="color: #ffb66c"><em>File&gt;Open</em></span> will enable us to open our scan. Then, going in Path&gt;Trace Bitmap… opens up a window. This window allows us to create a black-and-white vector file from our drawing via the “Single scan” tab. We can adjust parameters there, such as the threshold from which a zone is considered black or white, or the level of details that will be passed to your vector image. After clicking on <span style="color: #ffb66c"><em>Apply</em></span>, the vector image is created on top of the original one, which we can now delete. The result looks like this:</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"><img src="/blog/assets/img/inkscape_screen.png" alt="Screenshot of Inkscape" style="width:300px; height: auto;" class="center" /></p>

<p>     One can see on this screenshot the different points of the vector file, as well as the curves that connect them. Now, we can delete any point, move them around, change the shape of any curve, to obtain a satisfying result. (For example, I simplified a bit the cowlick on top of the sloth’s head.) When it is the case, one can save the file in <span style="color: #ffb66c"><em>.svg</em></span> format. This way, it can be included in a font.</p>

<h2 id="step-3-the-font">Step 3: The font</h2>

<p>     This step requires the help of another software: <a href="https://fontforge.org/en-US/">Fontforge</a>. It is also free and open-source, and allows to design custom fonts, which can later be used in any document. Once Fontforge is open, we can start a new font by clicking on <span style="color: #ffb66c"><em>New</em></span>. A table appears, with each square corresponding to a character. By importing a vector file for each character, we indicate what drawing should appear when the corresponding character is typed. If we were to design a standard font, we would add a drawing of the letter “A” in the square marked by “A”, a drawing of “B” in “B” etc … Here, we will use this grid to map our emoji to the keyboard.</p>

<p>     Double-clicking on any square opens a window. This window enables you to draw directly the corresponding letter, or to import an <span style="color: #ffb66c"><em>.svg</em></span> file. The latter option is done by going in <span style="color: #ffb66c"><em>File&gt;Import…</em></span>, selecting your vector file of choice, and selecting <span style="color: #ffb66c"><em>Import</em></span>. For the present case, I double-clicked on “A”, and imported the vector file shown previously. After that, one can just close this window, and the drawing is now visible in the global grid, under “A”.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"><img src="/blog/assets/img/screenshot_fontforge.png" alt="Screenshot of Fontforge" style="width:500px; height: auto;" class="center" /></p>

<p>     One can now generate the font file, which will enable the integration of our newly created emoji into documents (via Word, Pages, or any other word processing software), or into a Jekyll website. This is done by going in <span style="color: #ffb66c"><em>File&gt;Generate Fonts</em></span>. I then selected <span style="color: #ffb66c"><em>TrueType</em></span> as a format, which should change the extension of the created file to <span style="color: #ffb66c"><em>.ttf</em></span>. TrueType is a standard for fonts that is widely used and accepted by most softwares. I named the file <span style="color: #ffb66c"><em>CustomEmoji.ttf</em></span>. Now, our emoji is ready to be displayed on our website.</p>

<h2 id="step-4-using-it-in-jekyll">Step 4: Using it in Jekyll</h2>

<p>     We are almost done! To use our new emoji font, we need to show it to our software of choice. Many tutorials exist for Word, Pages or LibreOffice. This is done in Jekyll by first including it to the directory where your Jekyll project is. For the present website, I placed the font in <span style="color: #ffb66c"><em>assets&gt;fonts</em></span>, which is where I keep all the special fonts that I want to use for this website. Then, one needs to tell Jekyll where to go to find fonts. This is done by adding the following lines in the <span style="color: #ffb66c"><em>_config.yml</em></span> file:</p>
<pre>
<code>assets:
  sources:
    -assets/fonts</code>
</pre>
<p>Then, the font needs to be included to the layout of our page. This way, one can define a name for the font, and one can simply call the font by this name later on. I chose the name “Custom Emoji” for this font. This is done by modifying the file named <span style="color: #ffb66c"><em>variables.scss</em></span>, which is in the <span style="color: #ffb66c"><em>_sass</em></span> directory. Defining and naming a new font is then done by adding the following lines:</p>
<pre>
<code>@font-face{
	font-family: "Custom Emoji";
	src:url("../../assets/fonts/CustomEmoji.ttf");
}</code>
</pre>
<p>Of course, it is necessary to change the path to your <span style="color: #ffb66c"><em>.ttf</em></span> file according to your setup.</p>

<p>     And voilà! In any post written in Markdown, one can call our font named “Custom Emoji”, and just type the character “A” in this font, to see our emoji, perfectly integrated in the theme and layout of our Jekyll webpage!</p>

<p><span style="font-family: Custom Emoji;font-size: 62.0pt;">A</span></p>

<p>     The html line used to change the font locally is the following one:</p>
<pre>
<code> &lt;span style="font-family: Custom Emoji;
font-size: 62.0pt;"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt; </code>
</pre>

<p>     It is necessary to locally increase the font size so that the details of the drawing are visible enough. Not only can you now sign your posts in an original way, you can also put links on your emoji!</p>

<p>     Wishing you a lot of fun with your new emojis! <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dQw4w9WgXcQ"><span style="font-family: Custom Emoji;font-size: 62.0pt;">A</span></a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Programming" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[    Jekyll is probably the most famous static site generator today. It is free, open source and perfect if you need a personal webpage (like the one you are currently reading), or a page dedicated to a project. Many templates exist to help anyone make the best-looking page in a quick and easy way. However, one might want to put an extra personal touch to make the site more memorable and pleasant to navigate. This post proposes a tutorial to integrate custom emojis to your Jekyll webpage.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How I made myself a profile picture using AI</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/posts/codes/profile-picture/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How I made myself a profile picture using AI" /><published>2023-05-09T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-05-09T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/posts/codes/prof_pic</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/posts/codes/profile-picture/"><![CDATA[<p>    <em>While building this website, I put a picture of myself (the one that is now on the home page) in the sidebar. After uploading my first post, I started navigating from one page to another to check that everything was in its right place. As I was doing that, I felt my own picture watching me the whole time from the panel on the left. I wanted the work shown here to be linked to me but this felt … a bit too much. So I decided to change that.</em></p>

<p>     I wanted, as a sidebar picture, something more playful, but that could still identify me. With these constraints, a doodle of myself felt like a good solution. One tiny problem is that I am learning to draw, but I am definitely not there yet. I wanted everything to remain as cheap as possible, and I wanted to do it all by myself. So I asked the cartoonist that everyone talks about these days for help: Midjourney.</p>

<p>     I created an account and started playing with the AI. The idea of using Discord as an interface makes it very straightforward. (Tip: you can invite the bot in a private chatroom with yourself. This way, you are out of the constant flood of prompts from the other users.) As I said earlier, I wanted the picture to be playful, to represent creativity and curiosity, while also bringing science and engineering to mind. Therefore, I opted for pixel art. The prompt I used was the following one:</p>

<p><code> beardless man at computer with man bun and glasses, pixel art, minimalist, low resolution, low fidelity, warm colors, lights from the screen, cozy, end of afternoon </code></p>

<p>One of the result was the following picture:</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"><img src="/blog/assets/img/midjourney_raw.png" alt="The result of the prompt" style="height: 300px; width:300px;" class="center" /></p>

<p>     Believe it or not, if you have long hair and a light beard, you need to precise <code>beardless</code> in the prompt (and as you can see, the efficiency of it is not great). It makes sense after checking “Men with long hair” in Google, and seeing that long hair and big beards are apparently inseparable. (I promise that I do not only talk about <a href="/blog/posts/music/barber-beats/">haircuts for men</a> on this blog.) The point of precising <code>cozy, end of afternoon</code> was to suggest a window in the background, or an ambient light corresponding to these terms. As one can see, it did not really work out. Maybe this triggered the addition of the mug next to the computer, which is a rather nice touch?</p>

<p>     I thought that it was a very good base. The color palette is not great, and there are some odd features, such as the glasses. But overall, the assignment had been completed. The good thing with pixel art is that it is not unthinkable to try to adjust or correct an already existing material, even with basic skills in drawing. (Drawing something from scratch is, however, another story …) So I did using an open source tool that even runs on web browsers named <a href="https://github.com/piskelapp/piskel">Piskel</a>. I cannot stress enough how simple, straightforward and yet complete this software is. I used it to change some colors and correct minor mistakes in the picture and the result was the following one:</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"><img src="/blog/assets/img/git_avatar.png" alt="After the correction on Piskel" class="center" /></p>

<p>     I downscaled the picture to make it easier for me to edit, due to the lower amount of pixels. However, I still wanted to display the picture in a good quality everywhere I needed to. In a few lines, Python enabled me to rescale the picture as much as I wanted, and here we are! (This last step gave me an idea that I will expose in another post. Stay tuned!)</p>

<p>     The final result is now visible on the present sidebar, as well as on my GitHub profile. This could be improved, and is far from the quality, originality and customization that a human artist could have provided: I am completely dependent on the output of a machine … that is trained on pre-existing pictures. It also required my manual input at some point. However, few hours of work have brought me a result that is good enough for a personal blog, and that respected the two initial constraints: I was able to complete the whole process myself, and at no cost. In addition, this was possible without high skills in drawing, and using my eight-year-old computer that is now as powerful as a toaster and held together with duct tape. This gives me plenty of new ideas of things to try, that I will show around here.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Programming" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[    While building this website, I put a picture of myself (the one that is now on the home page) in the sidebar. After uploading my first post, I started navigating from one page to another to check that everything was in its right place. As I was doing that, I felt my own picture watching me the whole time from the panel on the left. I wanted the work shown here to be linked to me but this felt … a bit too much. So I decided to change that.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Barber Beats: modern impressionism</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/posts/music/barber-beats/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Barber Beats: modern impressionism" /><published>2023-01-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-01-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/posts/music/barber_beats</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/posts/music/barber-beats/"><![CDATA[<p>    <em>Picture this. You are about eleven or twelve years old. You wander in the aisles of a big supermarket, located at the bottom of a gigantic mall, on a saturday morning. Your mother is next to you, pushing the cart. Your father is at the front desk of the aforementioned supermarket, trying to return a set of undersized bed sheets bought last week. As the multitude of products goes by in front of your eyes, you get lost in your thoughts, and cling to the hope that your family will have lunch at the mall’s cafeteria. All this time, the faint, echoed music of the supermarket is sprinkled over each and everything, making up the soundtrack of your saturday’s daydream.</em></p>

<p>     A decade ago, I started realizing that the internet was a great source of music from times and places that were totally distant from me. The recommendation algorithms got better and better at providing me with hidden gems. One day, I stumbled upon this cryptic album cover, with inscriptions written with Japanese kanjis. An expression was written twice using the Latin alphabet, and it said: “HAIRCUTS FOR MEN”.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"><img src="/blog/assets/img/haircuts_for_men.jpg" alt="HFM cover" style="height: 300px; width:300px;" class="center" /></p>

<p>     Intrigued, I decided to listen to it. I was welcomed by some thick, distorted lounge music. I thought that I had just discovered a Japanese artist, straight out of the 1990s, with a funny name, who would provide me with some nice easy-listening tracks for studying or cooking. But I encountered Haircuts For Men (HFM) again few months later, on an even more cryptic cover, covered in cyrillic symbols this time. This led me to think that there was more to it than I thought.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"><img src="/blog/assets/img/haircuts_for_men_2.jpg" alt="Another HFM cover" style="height: 300px; width:300px;" class="center" /></p>

<p>    One noticeable thing about HFM is that their music is hardly present on any famous streaming platform, for a simple reason: almost none of their music is composed. The tracks are only remixes of existing lounge music tracks. These are usually slowed down, lowered in pitch, and a slight reverb and saturation are applied on them. Due to laws regarding copyrights, most of HFM’s work cannot be put on traditional music streaming platforms. Where is then the point in proposing music for which the melodies, the arrangements and the chord progressions are not original? In my opinion, the answer lies in what is around HFM’s music.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"><img src="/blog/assets/img/haircuts_for_men_3.jpg" alt="Another HFM cover" style="height: 300px; width:300px;" class="center" /></p>

<p>    What strikes first is the visuals for each of HFM’s projects. They combine images of unknown sources, representing semi-abstract shapes, often next to images of ancient Greek statues and non-Roman letters. Then, HFM’s username on Twitter is simply “@user080613”. Their bandcamp page proposes digital copies of their music for free, as well as vinyl and tape recordings of their catalog. For instance, the first album mentioned in this article is proposed, and the touch of spray paint is applied on the cover by the maestro themself. The customer cannot choose the color of the spray, it is chosen at random. Some “imperfect” versions are also proposed, for which the paint is not up to HFM’s standards.</p>

<p>    All these elements reinforce the slight feeling of unease going around HFM’s music. There is nothing wrong with their music, but something is definitely slightly wrong. It feels that, somehow, we should not have this music, this work, in our hands. It looks like it belongs to another time, to another place. It looks like, due to some malfunction of reality, this music from parallel dimensions has reached our ears.</p>

<p>    Lately, an internet legend has emerged. People online state that they have left (or “noclipped” out of) our dimension, and have arrived in what is referred to as a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Backrooms"><em>Backroom</em></a>, a place out of our reality, unsettling by its emptiness, not really hostile, not really welcoming. It is usually symbolized by vast open office spaces, or by abandoned shopping malls.</p>

<p>    All in HFM’s music relates to this last statement: not really hostile, not really welcoming, out of our reality. When looking for more detail about HFM, one can never be sure to have found a reliable source of information about them. Is it their Twitter account, or one of the many robots present on social media, or even a bug from the website, showing us unlisted users?  A very personal theory is that this nickname, <em>Haircuts For Men</em>, was chosen with that concealment purpose, as a simple Google search does not yield music but … pictures of haircuts for men.</p>

<p>    In the end, the work of HFM’s is here to make us feel things, rather than listen to things. It is designed to be the hidden, forgotten soundtrack of memories you never had, or memories you never thought you had, distorted and damaged by the passage of time. HFM’s music brings back that time you wandered in your high school around 7pm, when it is empty of all its students, or these saturdays when you mindlessly wandered in a huge supermarket, waiting for lunch. HFM has “an artistic style that seeks to capture a feeling or experience rather than to achieve accurate depiction”, which is the definition of impressionism according to Oxford Languages. Impressionism with a zest of modernity, as HFM uses a palette of techniques that are specific to the XXI<sup>st</sup> century and the digital world, to express feelings and emotions that are specific to the XXI<sup>st</sup> century and the digital world.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"><img src="/blog/assets/img/macroblank.png" alt="Macroblank cover" style="height: 300px; width:300px;" class="center" /></p>

<p>    HFM has had such an impact on the indie electronic wavy scene of the past years, that a whole subgenre has been named after them: Barber Beats. Other artists have joined the movement such as Macroblank (see picture above), or Monodrone (see picture below).</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"><img src="/blog/assets/img/monodrone.jpeg" alt="Macroblank cover" style="height: 300px; width:300px;" class="center" /></p>

<p>    This, to me, represents quite well some of the wonders of the internet. A person, somewhere on Earth, decided to depict modern feelings and concerns in an original way, without knowing that these would be relatable and shared by hundreds of thousands of anonymous people around the globe. From now on, I am very careful about the music I hear at the supermarket, and I hope your trips to buy groceries will also look a bit different. ;-)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Music" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[    Picture this. You are about eleven or twelve years old. You wander in the aisles of a big supermarket, located at the bottom of a gigantic mall, on a saturday morning. Your mother is next to you, pushing the cart. Your father is at the front desk of the aforementioned supermarket, trying to return a set of undersized bed sheets bought last week. As the multitude of products goes by in front of your eyes, you get lost in your thoughts, and cling to the hope that your family will have lunch at the mall’s cafeteria. All this time, the faint, echoed music of the supermarket is sprinkled over each and everything, making up the soundtrack of your saturday’s daydream.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PhD work</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/research/phd-thesis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PhD work" /><published>2022-12-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-12-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/research/phd-thesis</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/research/phd-thesis/"><![CDATA[<p>I have done my PhD between October 2019 and October 2022. I have worked during these three years at the Nuclear Physics Department of the French Alternative Energies and Atomic Energy Commission.</p>

<p>My thesis was divided into two parts:</p>
<ul>
  <li>one focusing on the study of the inelastic excitation of <sup>102</sup>Sn, <sup>100</sup>Cd and <sup>98</sup>Pd,</li>
  <li>the other one focusing on the study of the neutron-neutron correlations in <sup>11,13</sup>Li.</li>
</ul>

<p>Both are experimental works where I had to analyze large volumes of heterogeneous data. The results of these studies are exposed in the manuscript of my PhD thesis, available <a href="https://www.theses.fr/2022UPASP109">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have done my PhD between October 2019 and October 2022. I have worked during these three years at the Nuclear Physics Department of the French Alternative Energies and Atomic Energy Commission.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Master’s thesis work</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/research/master-thesis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Master’s thesis work" /><published>2022-11-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-11-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/research/master-thesis</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/research/master-thesis/"><![CDATA[<p>I have done my master’s thesis between January and June 2019 in the Mathematical Physics Department of Lund University, under the supervision of Dr. Gillis Carlsson and Dr. Andrea Idini. The pedagogical aim of this project was to work independently and build specialized knowledge around one topic of physics, which was theoretical nuclear structure in my case.</p>

<p>The objective of this work was to build an effective Hamiltonian representing the interactions at stake in the atomic nucleus. This has been done by extending such an operator proposed in 1970 by K. Kumar and B. Sørensen in 1970 <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/0375947470910821">[Nucl. Phys. A146 (1970) 1]</a>.</p>

<p>The manuscript I have written as a result of this study can be found <a href="https://lup.lub.lu.se/student-papers/search/publication/8986100">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have done my master’s thesis between January and June 2019 in the Mathematical Physics Department of Lund University, under the supervision of Dr. Gillis Carlsson and Dr. Andrea Idini. The pedagogical aim of this project was to work independently and build specialized knowledge around one topic of physics, which was theoretical nuclear structure in my case.]]></summary></entry></feed>